<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moral considerations touching the duty of contentedness under afflictions In a letter to the most affectionate and best of fathers Mr. James Simpson. By R.S.</title>
            <author>Simpson, Richard, 1661 or 2-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3819A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831090</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35552</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35552)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2112:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moral considerations touching the duty of contentedness under afflictions In a letter to the most affectionate and best of fathers Mr. James Simpson. By R.S.</title>
                  <author>Simpson, Richard, 1661 or 2-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by L. Lichfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.S. = Richard Simpson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Contentment --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35552:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35552:1"/>
            <p>MORAL CONSIDERATIONS TOUCHING The DUTY of CONTENTEDNESS UNDER Afflictions.</p>
            <p>In a LETTER to the moſt Affectionate and Beſt of FATHERS Mr. <hi>JAMES SIMPSON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By R. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35552:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35552:2"/>
            <head>MORAL CONSIDERATIONS Touching the Duty of <hi>CONTENTEDNESS</hi> under AFFLICTIONS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A midſt all my Afflictions, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing troubles me ſo much, as that, by the diſappointment of my hopes in this place, I am like to continue ſtill incapable of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome part of the Duty I owe You, in a way ſuitable to my Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. I mean, of giving you ſome handſome Evidence of my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement in my Studies. A thing I have alwaies infinitely deſired; having perhaps the greateſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to you that ever any ſon in the world had to a Father. But in the Circumſtances I am now in, cut off from the advantages of the <hi>Foundation,</hi> I muſt deſpair of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35552:3"/>doing any great matters in the way of a Scholar. All my concern is what I ſhall want in intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, to make up in Morals; and tho I may not be a great <hi>Clerk,</hi> yet to approve my ſelf, in the whole courſe of my Life and Actions, as I hope, I have hitherto done, a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Son, an honeſt Man, and a good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> In your laſt you were pleas'd to order me to ſend you ſome Conſiderations of my own pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, touching <hi>Contentedneſs under Afflictions.</hi> I have very readily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd your Commands; and ſuch poor indegeſted Collections as I could make upon this Subject, in the great trouble I am under, I now ſend you, wiſhing they may contribute ſomething to your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Comfort.</p>
            <p>Tho I am ſenſible, in handling this Argument I ſhall fall far ſhort
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35552:3"/>of my wiſhes, yet I have done (as under all the obligations of Duty and Gratitude I am bound) what I could to pleaſe and ſatisfy you, being ſtill deſirous (tho unable) in ſome meaſure to be a Comfort to you, and to Contribute ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Content and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Life. I have choſen rather to deſerve a check for my bad performance, than for my neglect; and had rather you ſhould be ſorry for my weakneſs, then my diſobedience.</p>
            <p>Tho, I muſt confeſs, I can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing but Candour and Kindneſs from you, in reference to what is here offer'd you, purely in obedience to your Commands; &amp; look for no worſe cenſure from the Tenderneſs of a Parent, then they uſually have that are making their firſt Eſſaies under a Writing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, whoſe firſt Copyes (tho
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35552:4"/>the Letters are awkwardly made and crooked) are ſmiled upon, not blam'd, rather pitied than reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now as I hope you will favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably look upon this ruffled, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed piece, and ſo lay it by; ſo I muſt earneſtly intreat you not to ſhew it to any curious eye, not to expoſe your ſon's imperfections to any Critical or Cenſorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for you ſee 'tis huddled up in a ſhort time, and wants all the Beauty and Ornaments of Method and Language.</p>
            <p>My retiredneſs and ſolitude (which I take a great delight in) has given me time and leiſure, for the thoughts I here ſet down, and my late misfortune abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupply'd me with Subject-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them. So that moſt of the Conſiderations I here preſent you with, are what every aſſault of grief, every ſad reflexion upon my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35552:4"/>late diſappointment here in the Colledge put me upon, whereby I endeavoured to ſettle and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my mind, to fit my ſelf as well for the ſincerity of Chamber and Chappel-Devotion, (a great part whereof you know conſiſts in hearty Thankſgiving;) as for the Company and Society of my Friends and Acquaintance. And I pray God theſe may prevail more, at leaſt as much, upon you, as they have upon me.</p>
            <p>You deſired a Letter of Advice and Comfort under your preſent preſſure and Trouble, or ſome <hi>Conſiderations touching the Duty of Contentedneſs under Afflictions.</hi> I have here (I ſay) ventur'd upon ſomthing in order to your ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. I ſhall not, dare not, yet meddle with any thing of <hi>Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but deſign only to let you ſee,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35552:5"/>how ſtrong and forcibly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive bare Morality is in this Point. And that I may not arrogate to my ſelf more than I ought, nor be juſtly condemn'd for a <hi>Plagiary,</hi> I hold my ſelf bound here ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to acknowledge, that much of what is here deliver'd, has been borrowed from the Elaborate Works of the more Learn'd Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then-Moraliſts, Latine and Greek Authours, who have writ upon this Subject, ſo that a great part of my ſmall pains in this buſineſs, has been to Collect, Tranſlate, and Methodize their Morality.</p>
            <p>The Ancient Moraliſts do uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally teach and enforce the <hi>Duty of Patience and Contentedneſs under Afflictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By ſhewing the neceſſity of ſubduing and regulating the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, (thoſe great diſturbers of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35552:5"/>the quiet &amp; ſerenity of the Soul,) and conſequently of acquiring a conſtant peace and tranquility of mind, and of living comfortably and contentedly under all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and circumſtances of life. For if the irregularity of Paſſion, be the grand cauſe of Diſcontent, and if (which is certain) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> be at all times the removal of the <hi>Effect</hi> too; then the Inference is plain and clear, That a due Government &amp; Regulation of our Paſſions, as it takes away all ſtruggling, diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and diſcompoſure of Spirit, ſo it leaves us in a quiet poſſeſſion of our own Souls, in internal peace and tranquility of mind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They enforce this Duty by laying down the neceſſity of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Submiſſion to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, in all the ſeveral diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of his Providence, as to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35552:6"/>Creatour and Governour of the World. For all the Heathen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts allowing the Exiſtence of a God, (a Natural Principle, and known to all men) they conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to be <hi>Infinitely Wiſe, Good,</hi> and <hi>Powerful:</hi> And from every one of theſe Attributes they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd a neceſſity of ſubmiſſion to, and acquieſcence in his pleaſure, as to the diſpoſal of all things in the world, <hi>viz.</hi> In reſpect of his Omnipotence, we ought to ſubmit to his Will out of plain and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Duty and neceſſity; In refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his Infinite Wiſdom, we ought to do in point of Prudence; In reference to his Infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we ought to do it in point of Gratitude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis the Abſolute and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſay Duty of every Rational Creature to Subdue and Regulate
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35552:6"/>the Paſſions, (thoſe great diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the peace and quiet of the ſoul) and conſequently to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and Content in all Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Circumſtances of life. For 'tis undeniably true, that if the due Order and Government of Paſſion removes all trouble and tumult, and diſquietneſs of mind from a man, then it leaves him in the enjoyment of all peace, tranquilty and ſerenity imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>i. e.</hi> gives him Patience and Content. For what is Quietneſs and Tranquillity of mind under Croſſes and Sufferings but <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi> What is Peace and Serenity of Soul under the loſs of Friends, Eſtate, Credit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but <hi>Contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> I ſhall therefore proceed to let you ſee diſtinctly,
<list>
                  <item>1. That the Irregularity of our Paſſions does really create alltheſe troubles and diſquiets, under
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35552:7"/>Croſſes and Diſappointments which give men ſo much unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py diſturbance and uneaſineſs, in their ſeveral Conditions; or that it is the Great Cauſe of Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</item>
                  <item>2. That 'tis the abſolute and neceſſary Duty of every Rational Creature, to Rule, Govern, and Diſcipline theſe Paſſions; to uſe his utmoſt Care and Endeavour, to bring them to a continued ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to his <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ſo introduce with eaſe into his Soul, a due, Comfortable and Sanctified uſe of all Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; in Proſperity, Thankfulneſs and Sobriety; in Adverſity, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs and Humility; in all, <hi>Moderation.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Inordinacy of Paſſion is the great Cauſe of Diſcontent. This I take to be ſo certainly and univerſally true that it may paſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35552:7"/>for an <hi>Axiom,</hi> or one of thoſe truths we call <hi>Firſt Principles,</hi> ſo as to need no demonſtration or proof.</p>
            <p>The great evil of ſuffering is not ſo much in the thing a man ſuffers, as in the mind and temper of the man, who meets with it. Impatience and Diſcontent come not ſo much from the ſtrength and force of any external Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as from the great Struggling, and reluctancy of the mind that ſuffers it. For take a humble, and moderate man, free from Pride, Haughtineſs, Covetouſneſs, and Ambition, how eaſily and ſoftly do Croſſes and Troubles fall upon him? With how much evenneſs and equality of temper does he recieve Calamities and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when God pleaſes to ſend them. The Reaſon is, his thoughts are prepared and qualified for it;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35552:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>he is maſter of himſelf, and his Paſſions; never tranſported or hurryed beyond what becomes a Reaſonable man; is all quiet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; does alwaies poſſeſs and enjoy himſelf in a happy peace and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity of ſoul, a conſtant ſetled compoſure of ſpirit. On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a Proud and Lofty man, ſwoln with the conceit of his own worth &amp; goodneſs, how does he ſtomack &amp; riſe at the leaſt diſappointment. Into what deſperate rage and choler does he throw himſelf upon any croſs or misfortune that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls him? He thinks Heaven obliged to favour his great me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and gratify his humour. And if diſhonour, reproach, poverty, loſs of eſtate or reputation, chance to happen to him, how much trouble and tumult, diſturbance &amp; diſcompoſure ariſes in the mind hereupon? How does the rage and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35552:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>boylings of ſuch an ones haughty, ambitious, and diſtemper'd ſpirit raiſe a ſtorm within him, that may poſſibly endanger the whole man; his ſtruggling galls worſe than the Yoke it ſelf otherwiſe would do; and he himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes infinitely more to his own uneaſineſs, than his Affliction doth. Again, 'tis the over-value we put upon Worldy goods, and the ſeeming bleſſings, and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies, they yeild us, that gives us ſo much trouble and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the loſs of them. What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite diſorders of mind do our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant deſires and longings after Riches create in us? What care and trouble to get them? What anxiety and reſtleſs fear leaſt we ſhould looſe them, when got? What infinite ſtrugglings and ſhiftings to keep them when they are going? And what extream vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35552:9"/>ſorrow and affliction when they are gone? So likewiſe 'tis the exceſs of love we undeſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place upon our health, pleaſure, reputation, greatneſs, honours, or the like, that makes us ſo una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to bear the loſs of them, by ſickneſs, reproach, poverty, or falſe friends, with that patience and quietneſs of mind which we ought. 'Twas <hi>Ahabs</hi> Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that made him troubled, and ſick, for a ſmall parcel of his neighbours ground. 'Twas <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s pride, ambition, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive love of Honour, that made him afflicted and diſcontented for the want of poor <hi>Mordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi>'s Knee. Whereas if our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of things here below were reaſonable and moderate, we ſhould be little or nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the want, or loſs of them: For it cannot greatly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35552:9"/>a man to part with what he never greatly cared for.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis certaine that Pride, Covetouſneſs, Ambition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which cauſe all diſcontent, and diſturbance of mind in us, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the Irregularities and exceſſes of paſſion; for the exceſs of ſelf-love is <hi>Pride,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy of deſire or delight, in the honours, or profits of this world, Ambition, Covetouſneſs <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that Pride, Covetouſneſs, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Intemperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> really cauſing all diſcontents; and theſe being nothing but the irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Paſſion; We muſt conclude the irregularity of Paſſion the Cauſe of all our Diſcontent.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A man ought therefore to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden himſelf of theſe original foundations of folly and miſery, to give a Law to the Senſitive Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, bring it into Subjection,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35552:10"/>and keep it within juſt limits and bounds, under the diſcipline and rules of Reaſon and Religion. Which is the next thing to be proved.</item>
               <item>2. 'Tis the Duty, I ſay, of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Rational Creature to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due, Govern, and Regulate his Paſſions, and to keep them in, that they may be in ſubjection, not in Dominion; may Serve, not Rule.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſenſitive Appetite (to which the Paſſions belong) is the Inferiour part of the Soul, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Dreggs of the people in a Government; of themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed apt to be heady, tumultuous, unruly, &amp; factious, if not reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Superiour power. Now God has committed this Appetite, with its Paſſions, to the Rule and Guidance of the Rational Soul, to the Government of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35552:10"/>Judgment and Underſtanding. It is therefore an Abſolute and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duty in the Soul or Mind, to exerciſe a due auſtere rule and ſuperintendency over theſe Subjects, and by no meanes to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them (through want of vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy and ſeverity in its Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration) to uſurp and prevail o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Judgment and Reaſon, and ſo invert the very order of Nature, by ſuffering the whole unhappy man to be carryed to ſerve the brutiſh luſts of an Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Licentious Appetite. She ought not to let them ſwerve from their due ſubmiſſion and conformity; leaſt they become rebellious, and bring in confuſion &amp; diſorder upon the whole Man. No, as God Almighty hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted the Soul of man as his Vicegerent in this Province which he hath committed to it, ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35552:11"/>he expects an account of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of this truſt, and will certainly puniſh the ſoul for the male-adminiſtration of its govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We are therefore under a great and ſtrong obligation to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and govern this Province to the glory of God. We ought to Reſolve and practiſe ſeverity over our unruly Appetites, to bring our Paſſions into order and obedience, to refuſe to gratifie their intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate deſires; to keep them in awe and under diſcipline; and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the whole <hi>Province</hi> to a due conſtant ſubjection.</p>
            <p>Again, the ſenſitive Appetite is Common to us with Brutes, and its inclinations, luſts, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are in a great meaſure the Law, in them and us. If men therefore ſet up their Paſſions for the Rule and Guide of their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if they will yeild to the crav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35552:11"/>of an importunate, inordinate, ſenſual Appetite, and to ſerve and obey their luſts; they are no way ſuperiour to the very Beaſts that Periſh. Now Almighty God hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given to mankind a higher, and a nobler Faculty, it ought in the very order of Nature to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, guide, moderate, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect that inferiour part which is common to us with Brutes: and that man that keeps not this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Rule of his nobler Nature over the lower Faculties of his ſoul, degrades himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Dignity of a <hi>Man,</hi> and having forfeited all the Royal Prerogatives of his Rational na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, debaſes himſelf to a parity with Beaſts; nay and below them too; for even theſe reſtrain their Appetites from Exceſs and Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>How admirably Great &amp; Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35552:12"/>ſeems that Noble temper of Mind, which is, Appoſitely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, called <hi>Equality of Humour!</hi> When a man keeps ſo much free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and liberty in his ſoul, as never ro be diſquieted; but as you leave him, ſo you find him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies indifferently chearful and ever the ſame. For is he rich, proſperous, great? yet he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues ſafe, becauſe he is ſtill hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thankful, watchful leſt he ſhould be deceived, or tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; careful leſt he ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed into Pride, Arrogance, Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, Preſumption. Is he poor, neglected, unfortunate? Yet he remains patient, humble content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thankful, depending upon that God he fears, looking up to the great Lord of Heaven and Earth, as knowing that he obſerves and eyes all men, and that his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence governs all things. And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35552:12"/>this keeps him ſtill even and ſquare without any conſiderable Alteration, whatſoever his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be. His Soul is lifted up above all thoſe inconſiderable toys the world ranges under the ſmiles and frowns of Fortune; and reliſhes more happineſs in a peaceable and quiet Spirit, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſerenity of Soul, then he could do in the enjoyment of all that others court with ſo much eagerneſs and ardour. How won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully happy is this temper of mind, how infinitely preferable to the diſorder and uneaſineſs of Impatience in moſt men! When if a man be rich, or powerful, there is nothing more vain, proud, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than he; but if poor, low, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, how does he ſink, and deſpond, and murmur and dye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Affliction! And there is nothing under Heaven more miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35552:13"/>and diſpairing than he. We muſt conclude him therefore hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to wonder and envy, whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit does not vary with his Fortune: Who ſcorns to let his Eyes be allways melting over a Remedileſs Evil, or ſuffer one Misfortune to ſwallow up all his Joys; but notwithſtanding all the Calamities that either lay upon him, or hang over him, he can preſerve a rare and happy Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his mind, which appears in an unclouded Serenity, that dwells always on his looks and diſcovers him ever <hi>Well pleaſed.</hi> So great is the advantage and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, that by a due rule, and Government of Paſſion does acrue to a wiſe man. And I ſhall venture confidently, Dear Sir, to affirm that this Freedom of Mind, and Serenity of Soul, ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd before the Empire of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35552:13"/>World. Beſides 'tis a true <hi>Maxim in Morality.</hi> He that commands himſelf, Commands the world too.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now proceed to Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularize the Paſſions, and ſhew the neceſſity of ſubduing each of them; I ſhould likewiſe here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon thoſe two known ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules, touching Regulation of Paſſions, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That they ought always to be determined to their proper objects. For Example, We ought to love and admire nothing but what is truly good, great &amp; highly valuable; nor hate and deſpiſe any thing, but what is bad, mean, and contemptible: fear nothing, but what is truly evil and hurtful: hope for nothing, but what is real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good and deſireable: rejoyce in nothing, but what will ſome way or other make us better: and ſo for the reſt.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35552:14"/>
            <p n="2">2. That being thus rightly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as to their objects, yet that they be not intended, nor acted beyond that degree that may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be allowed to the objects. Thus according to the ſeveral degrees of goodneſs and excellency in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects we ought to ſhare out unto them our love and deſires. The beſt and worthieſt ought to be proſecuted with the greateſt love and veneration. We ought not to love exceſſively what does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſo great a meaſure of it. So likewiſe we ought not to be angry for a longer time, or in a greater meaſure then the cauſe requires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But leaving theſe, I ſhall confine my ſelf to thoſe three Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which have a more eſpecial reference to my preſent purpoſe; <hi>Joy, Grief,</hi> and <hi>Deſire.</hi> A due regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of theſe being capable to render a man's mind quiet, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35552:14"/>conſtantly compoſed, his life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and happy. Treating of them in the particular relation they have to the good things of this world, and Firſt of</p>
            <p n="1">1. The moderation of <hi>Joy</hi> in the affluence of worldly things. The Conſideration of ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent good, belonging to us in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, begets in us that delight which we call <hi>Joy;</hi> and it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally defin'd to be a delightful commotion of the Senſitive Soul, as it were Triumphing in the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of preſent Good. Now that we may know how to regulate our <hi>Joy</hi> in the affluence of theſe things, We are to conſider the world, and examine whether thoſe things which our own thoughts, and the ſenſe of the Generality call Good, be really ſo, or no; and if ſo, what degrees of goodneſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35552:15"/>they have; that we may ſhare out to them, our eſteem, delight, and joy, accordingly. For, as I ſaid before concerning our Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in general, our delight and joy in the fruition of any Good is to be proportioned to the degrees of goodneſs in the object. Now we muſt grant that wordly things (as riches, honors, greatneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) are Good in their reſpective uſes, <hi>i. e.</hi> when they are honeſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the ſervice of God, and to his Glory: and conſequently we muſt allow a ſober, moderate Joy, in the fruition of them, and a chearful thankfulneſs to God for them. But 'tis againſt the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and Irregularity of Joy that I am ſpeaking, and do therefore affirm, that becauſe the Goodneſs and value of theſe things is really and truly very ſmall and ſlight, our <hi>Joy</hi> in the Affluence of them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35552:15"/>ought not to be great or exceſſive. For thoſe things which are very uncertain, very caſual, and withal many times extreamly dangerous to the Soul; which are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make us either better or wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; can ſcarce be ſaid to be Good. We have little reaſon therefore for any great or extravagant Joy, in the fruition of what we might as well (nay, perhaps more ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) be without, than have. I ſhall enlarge upon this Argument: Our Joy ought to be moderate as to theſe things. Becauſe</p>
            <p n="1">1. They onely concern this life, which is uncertain and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory, and paſſeth away. Theſe pleaſures of Sin endure but for a moment; our whole Life is no more. All the Good or Happineſs they do or can yield, is fadeing, and periſheth in the very Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35552:16"/>And beſides, a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, any little inconſiderable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, may put a Period to all theſe pleaſures, theſe delights, this life, in a year, in a week, in a day, in an hour, in a moment; and then theſe gawdy things leave us, and rather load and hinder the Soul in its flight to Heaven, than further it, in its Journey. A man ought therefore to have a low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for, and delight or joy in theſe tranſitory things; to keep himſelf in a conſtant love of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the things above.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Joy in the Affluence of worldly goods ought to be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, becauſe we ought to look upon all our plenty, greatneſs or proſperity, not as our own, or the reward of our own deſerts, but as the <hi>Depoſitum</hi> of the great Maſter of the family of Heaven and Earth:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35552:16"/>As Talents intruſted with us as Stewards, for our Maſters uſe, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and honour, not our own Grandeur, or pleaſure. We ought to conſider, that the more we have the greater are our Accounts, and the greater our charge. That God will moſt certainly reward our due and prudent Management of our Truſt and Steward-ſhip, and puniſh the contrary, and that to him we muſt certainly one day give an account of this our Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard-ſhip. That we are conſtantly under the view and obſervation, as well as under the care and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this our great Lord and Maſter, who expects we ſhould be moderate, watchful, and diſcreet in management of theſe outward things. So that our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and joy in the Affluence of them, ought not to be over great or exceſſive; ſeeing we can find
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35552:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>in them, no juſt motive to advance our thoughts, nothing to create any tranſport, triumph, or exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in us, but rather matter of diligence and care how to employ theſe Talents intruſted with us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our Joy ought to be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and little, if we conſider that there is a ſtrange kind of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft in theſe <hi>Worldly Goods</hi> to rob a man of vertue, and peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. They are dangerous temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to deceive us of our Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and Integrity. For we have obſerved, that upon the increaſe of theſe things, the Generality make Ship-wrack of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; become oppreſſive, proud and inſolent, diſorderly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd; perfect Worldlings, as tho they had never heard of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Hell, God, a Redeemer, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Judgment to come. Certainly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35552:17"/>therefore we ought not to pleaſe our ſelves too much in theſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous things, but be the more ſtrictly vigilant over our ſelves, keep a ſtrict gard over our hearts, leſt pride, or thoſe other vices and temptations, that haunt and wait upon worldly greatneſs, wealth and proſperity, ſhould ſteal in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us and ruine us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our Joy as to wordly goods ought to be moderate, becauſe, we ought to think and aim at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Ends, namely <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> to preſent to our thoughts a State of future happineſs, that far ſurpaſſes any this world is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of yielding. We are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that this world, and all that we call <hi>Good</hi> in it, is vexed with evils, with fears, with viciſſitudes of ſorrow and trouble, but that the happineſs of the next is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſincere, and unmixt with any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35552:18"/>thing that may allay it; we ought not therefore to fix upon this world, or throw too great a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of love, delight or joy, upon any thing in it, 'tis all nothing, and Vanity; but we ought to ſet up our Hope, Joy, Happineſs and reſt in another world; eſpecially knowing that this lower world is onely the place of our Probation, not of our Happineſs; our Inn, not our Home.</p>
            <p>I have inſiſted the longer upon this moderation of our Joy in the Affluence of Riches, Honors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In order to the great <hi>Duty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs,</hi> becauſe in Experience we find thoſe of all others moſt apt to be dejected and afflicted by the frowns of Adverſity, who have already been deceived, and puft up, with the Flatteries of Proſperity; And 'tis certain they that think the gain of worldly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35552:18"/>things to be but ſmall, will think the loſs ſmall too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The moderation of <hi>Grief</hi> in the loſs of the <hi>Good things</hi> of this life, is the Second thing I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to treat of, as a means to gain <hi>Content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Grief is a ſad dejected <hi>languor</hi> of the Soul, under the preſſure of ſome <hi>preſent Evil.</hi> Now (as we did before) we are to ſee firſt whether the loſs of theſe worldly things be really <hi>Evil,</hi> and if ſo we are to examine its meaſure or degree of <hi>Evil,</hi> that accordingly we may proportion our Grief. Now, I have already granted the things of this world to be ſome way <hi>Good</hi> (namely in their due and regular uſe) and muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grant the Loſs of them to be ſome way <hi>Evil;</hi> (for to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of what is in ſome meaſure
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35552:19"/>
               <hi>Good,</hi> is in ſome meaſure <hi>Evil,</hi>) and conſequently allow ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of <hi>Grief.</hi> But then they muſt have nothing of Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, or Irregularity in them, they muſt not be accompani'd w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> bitter invectives againſt ſecond Cauſes, or Inſtruments, they muſt not reflect upon Gods Juſtice, nor revile his Providence; but muſt be full of Submiſſion, rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing our Humility, then our Anger. I am, I ſay, againſt all manner of Exceſs. For as that value or Portion of <hi>Goodneſs</hi> I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to worldly things, was ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſmall, as likewiſe the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> in the increaſe of them, was to be light and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; ſo the loſs of them is little or no <hi>Evil;</hi> and conſequently the <hi>Grief</hi> for it muſt be little or none; a man is ſeldome ſorry to looſe what he doth not much value;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35552:19"/>and it would ſcarce trouble a Wiſe man to part with what is very often more ſafely loſt then kept. For in the loſs of Honors or Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, our accounts are the leſs, our temptations not ſo dangerous, our cares fewer; and generally in all Afflictions and Loſſes, our Leſſons of Dependance upon God, of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and lowlineſs of mind, of temperance and ſobriety, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world, of our love of Heaven, are much better Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then in the increaſe and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of <hi>Worldly Goods.</hi> Briefly therefore, As the Acquiſition or increaſe of Riches, Honors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ought not to be the object of any ſtrong deſire, or joy; ſo neither ought the Decreaſe or Loſs of them, to cauſe any great Grief or Sorrow. <hi>Gods Will be done,</hi> ought to be the Language of every wiſe and good Soul in relation to them.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:35552:20"/>
            <p>How have the Heathen Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts adorn'd this Subject! How many curious Expreſſions, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Moderarion of <hi>Grief,</hi> in their Writings! Nay (to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of thoſe Eminent Authors, who tied their Studies and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to this expreſs Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) The Poets, whoſe Themes were generally Caſual, and Light, and their Poems, the Productions of a roveing, idle fancy; yet even upon this Excellent Subject, have they given us brave and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Strokes. A noble Spirit muſt not vary with Fortune; for as no Condition is ſo high, as to be out of the reach of fears, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is any ſo low, but may have hopes. That Adverſity overcome is the higheſt Glory, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undergone, the greateſt Vertue; Sufferings being but the tryal and touch-ſtone of Gallant-Spirits.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35552:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>That Impatience and Complaint ſhew a narrowneſs, or weakneſs of Soul, according to the old Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im: <hi>Invalidum omne natura que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relum.</hi> The more weak any thing is the more apt to complain. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the more we ſtruggle with our Yoke, the more 'twill hurt us. That the only allay under great Sufferings is to bear them quietly and obey Neceſſity; to ſubmit to what we cannot remedy. But without enlarging upon theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent peices of Morality, let us go on. We have no great reaſon for exceſſive <hi>Grief</hi> in the Loſs of <hi>Worldly Goods,</hi> if we conſider that the loſs of Friends, and Relations comes from the common condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Nature, and from the very notion of Morality; And can we think, that the very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things ought to be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to pleaſe our humors? The
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35552:21"/>loſs of Goods, Riches, Wealth, is for the moſt part by Thunder, or Storms, or Tempeſts, or Fire; the loſs of health from the Intempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Air, or Meteors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And can we rationally expect that the great God of Heaven ſhould alter the ſetled Laws of Nature, for the convenience, or profit of ſuch Worms as we? In a word, the Courſe of the world is ſuch that Croſſes and Afflictions muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity come; And therefore why ſhould any man ſink into deſpair or diſcontent, becauſe the world does go, as it always did, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows its own natural State and Condition.</p>
            <p>Many times when I have known my Friend dead, I could have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed my Face with Tears, and as paſſonately have wept over his ſacred Urn, as I ever rejoyc'd in the happineſs of his Company,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35552:21"/>while living: But I reſolved to lay aſide my trouble; when I had conſidered, that it was more Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in me then Prudence. For I might as reaſonably have wept that my Friend was born no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as that he ſhould live no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Thus I cannot but interpret even that extraordinary concern, SIR, you have expreſs'd upon my late diſappointment in this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege. It ſignifies indeed rather a deal of tenderneſs and affection, than (allow me I beſeech you the Inſolence of the Expreſſion for once) of true wiſdom and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. You might with almoſt as much reaſon grieve that I was ever born into the world, as that I ſhould receive troubles and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in it. This world is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a heap of Cares, Anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Miſeries, with which every rank of men and ſtate of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35552:22"/>life is beſet. <hi>Man is born to Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the ſparks fly upward;</hi> ſaith that great Example of Patience, and Reſignation, <hi>Job.</hi> So com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and univerſal is an afflicted condition of life to poor Mortals, that it ſeems to be as natural as that propriety in Fire to aſcend. Nay our very entrance into the world, ſeems to acquaint us with the Entertainment we are like to have in it ever after. Our firſt Minutes being attended with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and pain, and 'tis certainly ominous to the remainder of our life, that we are born <hi>Crying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then no Perſon howſoever Good, Juſt, Wiſe, and Pious, of what Age, Sex, Degree, Quality and Profeſſion ſoever, could ever yet boaſt an Exemption from this Univerſal State and Condition of Humane life; we may as juſtly grieve that God has given us life,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35552:22"/>and made us men, as that in this life we ſhould meet with Trouble and Afflictions, the common Lot of Mankind. We ought therefore chearfully and contentedly, to bear <hi>theſe light afflictions which endure but for a moment,</hi> and (to ſpeak with the forementioned Heathen Author) ſubmit patiently to what we cannot remedy.</p>
            <p>Give me leave now to venture upon a Word or two of Advice, in order to the preventing all exceſs of <hi>Grief</hi> under croſſes and misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Reference to any croſs, or ill ſucceſs in buſineſs, or failure in any undertaking. Take heed of being too ſolicitous about the Iſſue of things, and of determining your ſelf too peremptorily, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Events. 'Tis indeed our buſineſs to ſerve Providence in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35552:23"/>uſe of means, But to God alone belongs the Iſſue of Things; and that which is not within our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ought to be out of our care. If therefore ſucceſs of buſineſs doth not at firſt anſwer your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let no fumes of Melancholy poſſeſs you. Uſe other Expedients and Addreſſes, but do not by any means engage your Affections too paſſionately in it, nor promiſe your ſelf ſucceſs; ſo you will not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed if you miſcarry, which you muſt make account will often happen to you. For all things by nature in the Univerſe are ſubject to a continual change, and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And there is no Conſtancy either in the favour of Fortune or minds of men; ſo that no wiſe man can either wholly truſt to the one, or depend upon the other. Expect therefore often to be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and then you will not be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35552:23"/>diſquieted when the fruſtration comes. For what you do poſſibly look for, is come to paſs, and what ſhould amaze you? That which hath happened now, is but what you have often ſeen and known; and what ſhould either ſurprize, or diſquiet you?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Endeavour by frequent An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of affliction and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes to habituate and fit your mind for them, when they do come: For theſe thoughts will furniſh you with a ſuitable tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, for them, render them eaſy to you, and keep your Soul in a due State of watchfulneſs and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before they come. Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makes the deepeſt impreſſion, when it ſurprizes us, and comes unexpected; becauſe it takes a man upon the ſudden, and before he can compoſe himſelf, or rally
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35552:24"/>the ſuccours of reaſon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to ſupport him againſt it. It is like a ſuddain diſeaſe that ſurprizeth the body labouring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ill humours, before it has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and allay'd theſe humours by preparative helps or Cathar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. And then many times more danger ariſes from the diſcompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the humours, then from the malignity of the diſeaſe it ſelf. But if the mind be prepared for troubles and croſſes, by a kind of Anticipation, this abates the edge, keenneſs, and ſharpneſs of them, and makes them fall light, and eaſy upon us. Now if in that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious change and revolution of events which we behold in the world, we do not look upon poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible croſſes and troubles as future, we loſe our ſelves in a dangerous ſecurity, and are little better then mad-men. Where therefore we
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35552:24"/>ſee at any time the loſſes and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, poverty, and misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of others, we ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently reflect, <hi>this, tho at preſent it is not, yet may be ſhortly our own caſe.</hi> Thus the ſtroke of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune will have leſs force and ſmart, which is wiſely foreſeen, expected, and provided againſt. By this means a man in a great meaſure knows the worſt of them, before he feel them, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them a great deal more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and eaſy. And by thus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipating what we have juſt cauſe to fear, and putting our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pre-apprehenſion of it, we learn the Leſſon of Patience, and Reſignation before we have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to uſe it. Thus we are prepared to entertain Affliction with Courage and Chriſtian for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Thus we habituate our minds to a chearful and due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of them.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:35552:25"/>
            <p>But as to this, I deſire, SIR, to be rightly underſtood. I would not have this Anticipation ſo wholly to poſſeſs your Soul as to ſpoil the fruition, and take away all the lawful pleaſures and comforts of thoſe worldly bleſſings God is pleaſed to allow you. No; This were to let the thoughts of <hi>Evil</hi> ſwallow up the reliſh and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Good;</hi> this were to let your fears drive away all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, ſerenity and happineſs out of your mind, and yet never cure nor remove the danger. As therefore the increaſe and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the many <hi>Good</hi> things of this life, as the height of Proſperity ought not to delude us ſo far, as never to think of a poſſible Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation in our condition, (for tho we are now healthy and rich, we muſt think there will come a time when we ſhall be ſick and under
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35552:25"/>misfortunes.) So we ought to be careful, that the overmuch thought of this change and alteration, in our Condition, theſe poſſible croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and misfortunes, do not ſo much poſſeſs our ſouls, as to make us forget the Goodneſs of God, in beſtowing theſe good things upon us, or neglect that duty we owe to God for them, <hi>viz.</hi> An honeſt &amp; charitable uſe of them in our callings, relations, places and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, a hearty, chearful, and yet with all a ſober and moderate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and ſatisfaction in theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, lawful, Comforts of life, and all poſſible praiſe and thanks-giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that God, that hath been pleaſed by entruſting us with theſe things, to make our lives ſome way ſerviceable to him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to others, and comfortable to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Think therefore that things
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35552:26"/>may be a great deal worſe than they are now, and that however they be, you ought to acquieſs in in the will and pleaſure of God concerning them; but ſtill be thankful for what you have, truſt Providence for the future; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hope the beſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I come now to the due Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of our <hi>Deſires</hi> in the want of what the World calls <hi>Good.</hi> And 'tis certain that almoſt the whole Art of Attaining to that happy, contented ſtate of life,) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we are inquiring) conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the due regulation and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our deſires. For that mind can never be contented, that (having not regulated its <hi>Deſires</hi>) is too furiouſly bent upon the world, and thoſe things which our own vain thoughts, and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken eſtimate of the generality
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35552:26"/>of men call <hi>Good</hi> in it; that ſtill runs before that ſtation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition God Almighty hath order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it; and tho it attains this year what it earneſtly perſued the laſt, yet ſtill it will be gadding far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and keep before its Acqueſts. Its thoughts and endeavours are reſtleſs, and ſtill aſpiring and aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing higher, and ſo it can never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy what it hath, becauſe it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies buſies it ſelf too much in the anxious purſuit of what it hath not. Whereas if a man would but bring himſelf and his thoughts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a low and juſt eſteem of this world, and all the gawdy vanities in it; if he would moderate his deſires and keep them either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and below, or at leaſt equal with that Station of life Divine Providence and honeſt Induſtry, has alotted him, he might enjoy his Eſtate comfortably and happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35552:27"/>and poſſeſs his Soul in peace and quietneſs.</p>
            <p>Now that our deſires may be within their due bounds, and not run gadding after what they ought not, nor be ſo irregularly bent upon things often falſly ſtil'd <hi>Good.</hi> We ought carefully to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them aright, <hi>i. e.</hi> to things which we clearly and diſtinctly know to be really <hi>Good:</hi> And the on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly way ſo to direct them is, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our underſtanding or faculty of diſcerning (which God to that end hath given us) ſtrictly and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively to examine and conſider, the real goodneſs of theſe things, and its meaſure; that accordingly we may determine our will, to affect, and earneſtly perſue them, or be indifferent towards them, and fix our Affections upon high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and nobler objects.</p>
            <p>We are therefore to look ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35552:27"/>into Riches, Honours, Pleaſures and Greatneſs; and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are not uncertain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving things, what Stability there is in them, what good they will do after death; what quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or tranquility they will yeild us, or rather take from us, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have in them any real influence to make us better or wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. And when we find (as we needs muſt) that they have no Stability in them, will do us no Good after death; we are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to withdraw all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of love and deſire, from them, and ſet up our hopes and hearts upon more noble and more durable enjoyments.</p>
            <p>Honors and greatneſs are known to be rather dangerous and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, than deſireable; rather Curſes than Comforts and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. Envy, Malice, Jealouſy,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35552:28"/>and an infinite number of ſins and diſturbances always attend them. They make Thrones, but uneaſy Seats, and Honors no more than ſplendid Miſeries. We ought to conſider them as Gilt that covers a bitter Pill; and looking through this dreſs, and outſide, eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that it conceals a State ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to danger, ſolicitude, care, trouble, envy, diſcontent, unqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs, and infinite temptations. A Condition, which, if there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen any alteration or change in the Adminiſtration of Goverment, any diſtemper or rebellion in the Nation, any faction among the <hi>Grandees,</hi> or Inſurrection among the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> will be infallibly hunted after, puſht at, and ruin'd: So that Honor is rather a Burthen, than a Priviledge; it makes our charge and our accounts the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; our reſt, and contentment the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35552:28"/>leſs. And we may find enough in great imployments to make us ſenſible of the dangers, troubles, and uneaſineſs of them, enough to make us humble; but nothing to make us proud or haughty, or create any great love and deſire of them. To be ſhort, the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and folly of Greatneſs, the vanity of Pleaſures, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of Riches, make up a great part of the Writings of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Modern and Ancient Authors. I ſhall not then give you, or my ſelf, the trouble of tedious proving and inſiſting upon that, which all-moſt every Book you meet with will do for me. Onely give me leave to inſiſt a little particularly upon that immoderate Love and <hi>Deſire</hi> of Riches, which is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in the generality of men. The getting and increaſing of Eſtates, is ſo much the Buſineſs
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35552:29"/>of Mankind, as if they at the ſame time in buying of Lands purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Salvation and Eternal Happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to themſelves. To let alone all the dangers, cares, and other ill conſequences of <hi>Riches,</hi> ſtill Mortality, Death, and the Grave terminate all the fading felicity they do, or can yield us; and the fear, and pre-apprehenſion of ſuch an end ſhould be apt, one would think, to ſower and allay even that comfort and pleaſure which theſe would perhaps otherwiſe offer. This one thought is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to embitter their enjoyment, and render them inſipid. 'Tis like the Worm at the bottom of the Gourd, that withers and ſpoils their fruition, and puts the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them out of the capacity of making us happy. For great cares, and great fears, can never conſiſt with true happineſs.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:35552:29"/>
            <p>Riches, I grant, were to be ſought after above all other things, if they brought content or peace of Soul (the greateſt bleſſing of life) along with them. But Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts and Philoſophers do uſually teach us that <hi>Content</hi> dwells not in Courts and Palaces, or Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes, but in Hermitages and amongſt Shepheards and Swains: Where free not only from the Turmoyle, and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the world, but even from all Idle, Vain, and Ambitious thoughts and deſires, (thoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral cauſes of diſcontent) The poor man learns ſeriouſly to veiw the Vanities of the world in their full proportion, and ſo to deſpiſe them. Where he likewiſe can with chearfulneſs and innocent joy look upon the honeſty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, that little ſtock of <hi>Goods,</hi> God is pleaſed to allow
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35552:30"/>him; and living in great tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and ſatisfaction of mind at preſent, for the future with an humble ſubmiſſion refers himſelf to Providence. Thus the Poor, but honeſt Cottager, that patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endures his Wants, is rich e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and by his continued ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity of mind, invites <hi>Content</hi> to come and dwell with his humble Fortunes; whileſt the Greedy Miſer, that ſpends his time, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, life, and very ſoul in ſcrape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wealth together, is never ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfed, never content, never at reſt. For Experience hath made it a <hi>Proverbial truth—The more a man hath, the more he wanteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here to make a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</p>
            <p>When my late misfortune put me upon ſolitude, I took delight in walking alone in the Meadows
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35552:30"/>and Paſtures near this place; to obſerve the ſimplicity, ſincerity, and innocency I fancied in the Country Swains and Shepheards; I was hugely taken with the calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſecurity, as likewiſe with the honeſt pains and induſtry of that manner of life, where they meet not with any occaſions, or opportunities of doing ill, have no alluring Temptations to ſin or vanity, no Cares, no Troubles to diſturb the peace and tranquillity of their minds. And here, to lay my heart naked and open before you, and let you read there my inmoſt thoughts, wiſhes, and deſires, I muſt confeſs, was I to diſpoſe of my condition of life, according to my own inclination, I ſhould pitch upon this before any other. I ſhould willingly chuſe to be, as thoſe Swains and Shepheards of old, who tuned their <hi>Oaten-Reeds</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:35552:31"/>at the foot of mount <hi>Ida,</hi> or upon the Banks of <hi>Tiber,</hi> ſo much cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated by the Curious pens of <hi>Theocritus</hi> and <hi>Virgil.</hi> And here bidding <hi>farewel</hi> to the Noiſe, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, Ambition, and Inquietudes of the world, I would give up my ſelf to repoſe, and ſolitude, to the pleaſant retiredneſs of the Fields and Woods, where having leſs of Vanity, but more of Prudence, leſs Pride, but more Virtue, leſs Ambition, but more Content, I ſhould fancy to meet with all the Remainders of the Primitive <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en-age,</hi> and almoſt all the bleſſings of <hi>loſt Paradice.</hi> Where I might without interruption not only ſtudy the Book of Nature, as deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to us in the elaborate gloſſes of <hi>Ariſtotle, Pliny,</hi> &amp;c. but have leiſure enough more ſenſibly to contemplate all the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, which are legible, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35552:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſpicuous in the Creation, loſe my ſelf in admiration of thoſe vaſt Moveables that adorn the higheſt Regions of the world, look upon with wonder and amazement, Natures curious and unimitable Workmanſhip in every Flower and Herb of the Field; might diſcern the being of a God, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very inferiour Creature, and in their fitneſs and convenience for man's uſe, read that propriety he has in them; to be ſhort— Every where meeting with freſh Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Divine Goodneſs, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and bounty, of his Power, Majerty and Glory, of his Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Providence and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which are, (at leaſt ought be) ſo many precepts to learn us, to know, admire, and magnifie him,) behave our ſelves thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, dutifully, and obediently to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him; ſo many inſtructions
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35552:32"/>to teach us Reſignation, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſs, Submiſſion, and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon him.) Every where (I ſay) diſcerning the Admirable Inſtances of <hi>Providence</hi> and a <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> I might wiſely diſpoſe and fill my mind for the reception of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limer truths; Thus happily ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my daies in Contemplation of God and his myſterious works, till I came to the accompliſhment and completion of Knowledge in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, where I ſhould ſpend not only my <hi>time,</hi> but Eternity it ſelf, in what I here imperfectly begun.</p>
            <p>But to Proceed.— I could eaſily prove this Paradox; That, what is beyond that which is purely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, is uſeleſs, That he whoſe poſſeſſions are in a reaſonable manner proportionable to the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of his condition of life, and will afford him and his a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35552:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>livelihood, is really rich e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. That nothing of ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or redoudance can be of any ſervice or uſe to us, becauſe we ſtand in no need of it, have enough without it. That money and wealth which is over and above what ſerves for our preſent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and the ſupport and maintenance of our Families, is indeed our Burden, our Care, and Trouble, but is of no more uſe to us in our Cheſts, than if it were in the Center of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever therefore is more than enough for our natural ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and the neceſſary ſupply of our Families, and is ſo imployed, is in truth needleſs, uſeleſs, and unſerviceable; becauſe the only uſe of externals, is to ſupply natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral neceſſities. Unleſs in an Age of Univerſal Indevotion, you would think of reviveing that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquated
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35552:33"/>Cuſtome of putting out your Spare-money to Charitable uſes, as Buildings, and Endowing Churches, Colleges, Hoſpitals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that 'tis not the uſe but abuſe of Redundance and Superfluities, that we may dayly obſerve in all manner of Exceſs, either in eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or drinking, in gratifying our Luſts, Pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from diſcourſes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would be, that the deſires of men in reference to this life, and its enjoyments, ought not to be laviſh, and extravagant, in gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding after redundance of Wealth, and Riches, but to be terminated in things of neceſſity, for their preſent ſubſiſtence, convenient Food and Raiment for them and theirs; and that if it pleaſe God to allow us a Sufficiency and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency for the Neceſſities of our Natures, and the honeſt ſupply
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35552:33"/>of our families, we have great reaſon to be contented with it, not only as it is a duty enjoyn'd us, but upon moſt evident conviction of ſound reaſon.</p>
            <p>Not that any thing we ſay of this kind ſhould encourage any man to be careleſs and remiſs in his Buſineſs, or Trade, nor hinder him from imploying himſelf with honeſty and diligence, in that Temporal calling and ſtation Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath placed him in. No; tho we ought not to ſet our hearts upon the conveniencies of this life, yet we are not to reject them, but to uſe them ſoberly &amp; thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, for they are Bleſſings that deſerve our gratitude, tho they ought not entirely to take up our thoughts, or deſires. God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty has allowed and indulg'd a moderate care to get theſe <hi>goods</hi> and uſe of them when got, as in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35552:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>the competent ſupplies of our Natue with Neceſſities, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for our Families, Relations, Dependencies; the diligent and faithful walking in our Callings, and diſcharge thereof; but all this is to be done without Covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and a too eager perſuit after theſe things. And there is a buſineſs of greater importance, which without any neglect of what is neceſſary to be done, in order to the common neceſſities of our lives and Callings, we ought chiefly to place our endeavours upon, <hi>viz.</hi> Our Proviſion for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, and Salvation.</p>
            <p>I ſhould likewiſe here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that Golden Mediocrity, (a ſtate of life wherewith I hope, <hi>Sir,</hi> you are at preſent bleſt) ſo much celebrated by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; I mean that ſafe and Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35552:34"/>Condition, which places a man below Envy, and yet above Contempt. A Condition, in which 'tis certain a man cannot by any enlargement of his Fortune be made either more rich (in a true ſenſe) or more happy. For on one ſide a State or Condition too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for our neceſſities, of Want and Poverty, is ſubject to ſo many troubles and temptations, that it requires a very conſiderable ſtock of Patience and Humility, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo it; and on the other, an Eſtate of Grandeur, Wealth, and Power, beſides its uſual dangerous and deadly effects, as Pride, Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, oppreſſion, forgetfulneſs of God, and Heaven, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> it makes the perſon that has it onely an object of Envy to all other men; which being a buſy, reſtleſs, and pernicious humour, always find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faults, ever picking, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35552:35"/>quarrels, and carrying them on very often to dreadful Iſſues; does eternally ſtudy, and endeavour the ruine of its object. A man ought therefore withal thankfulneſs to acknowledge both the Wiſdom and Goodnefs of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in giving him ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, and ſo ſafe a Condition, by which he does deliver him from all the difficulties, and inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, dangers, and temptations of both extreams, great Want, and great Wealth.</p>
            <p>But if I ſhould begin with theſe now mentioned diſcourſes, enter upon the proof and enlargement that ought to be made upon each of them, I ſhould ſwell too big, (the ſubject being very large and copious.) I ſhall therefore wave them, and onely deſire you not to ſuffer your ſelf to be too much engaged in the cares of this life,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35552:35"/>taking thought (that I may uſe inſpir'd Expreſſions) what you ſhall eat, or what you ſhall drink, or where withall to be clothed; But having by honeſt labour and induſtry done your part, I would intreat you chearfully to commit your ſelf to Almighty God, <hi>Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all your care upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Second general Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was.—'Tis a neceſſary and abſolute Duty in every man to ſubmit to, and acquieſce (conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly) in, <hi>God Almighties</hi> will and pleaſure, in all the ſeveral dealings and diſpenſations of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. And that upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of his Omnipotence.</item>
               <item>2. Of his Infinite Wiſdom.</item>
               <item>3. Of his Infinite Goodneſs.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. We ought to ſubmit to, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35552:36"/>acquieſce in that will and pleaſure of <hi>God,</hi> conſidered as an Almighty Being.— A humble Soul, like a white Sheet of Paper, muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receive whatever the hand of God ſhall imprint upon it, ſays an Excellent Heathen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt. He is certainly both Fool and Mad-man, who ſtruggles with Omnipotence, and moſt egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wicked, that while under the Rod of Affliction dares mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur at, and revile Providence, as to the Government of the World; and does not rather correct and amend himſelf, and reſolve to put a Period to his ſins and provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that <hi>God</hi> may put a Period to his Puniſhments. No man did ever ſet upon a due and attentive Contemplation of the Power, Greatneſs, and Majeſty of <hi>God,</hi> but beſides his being ſtruck into Amazement and Extacy, he would
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35552:36"/>proſtrate himſelf in the Duſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging himſelf to be but a poor Worm, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely unworthy to diſpute the diſpenſations, and providences of ſo great and glorious a Being. And without all doubt, if we were but under a conſtant, firm, Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he is a moſt Powerful, Wiſe, and <hi>Almighty God,</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all things; Preſent in all places; who knows our thoughts, our deſires, our wants; of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Wiſdom, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable <hi>Power;</hi> is abundantly able to ſupply us with all things, that are good &amp; fit for us, beyond what we are able to ask, or think; that he leaves not any of his works, eſpecially Mankind, without his ſpecial care and ſuper-intendance over them; That he is the great diſpenſer of all things; may even upon account of his <hi>Soveraignty</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35552:37"/>whatever he pleaſes, upon any of his Creature, having an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and unlimited propriety in them, to diſpoſe them, according to his good pleaſure: I ſay, if we were but under a conſtant, ſound Conviction that theſe things are really and undeniably true, we ſhould queſtionleſs chearfully and freely ſubmit to the dealings and diſpoſals of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever grateful or diſtaſtful to our preſent ſenſe. For how dare any man murmur at the diſpoſal the <hi>God</hi> of Heaven makes? What have you or I to do to invade his Prerogatives? Or why may we not as reaſonably refuſe to obey <hi>God</hi> in what he commands, as to ſubmit to him, in what he inflicts? Again, <hi>God</hi> hath made the <hi>Order</hi> and Government of the World ſuch, that it is abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that if ſome be rich, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35552:37"/>Great and Honorable; others muſt be poor, and ſubject, mean and neglected. If all were <hi>equally ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable,</hi> we ſhould loſe the very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Being of <hi>Honor;</hi> becauſe there is no <hi>Honor</hi> where there is no <hi>Superiority,</hi> (Which we muſt not ſuppoſe in a State of <hi>Equality</hi>) honor, being a preference given to ſome perſons, for their Wiſdom, Vertue, or other extraordinary Merits above other men. And if all were equally <hi>Powerful,</hi> there would be no <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> at all; the very Notion of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment inferring <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> ſuppoſing <hi>Superiority.</hi> Why therefore ſhould not you or I be content to be of the lower ſort of men, ſince the order, frame, and texture of the world requires that ſome ſuch there muſt be? Or why ſhould we be ſo unjuſt and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, to deſire that the lot of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35552:38"/>Poverty, or Meanneſs of Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be other mens, and not ours? Or if we refuſe it, why may not other men with as much Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Juſtice on their ſides, do ſo likewiſe? If therefore <hi>God</hi> ſhall pleaſe to give us, Wealth, Honor and Proſperity, we muſt be thankful, and careful to employ theſe Bleſſings to Gods Service and Glory; If not, we are ſtill to be patient and content; and what ever our Circumſtances be, we are oblig'd under the greateſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of Reaſon and Equity to a quiet and patient, nay more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, to a free, and chearful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with that State, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of life, <hi>God Almighty</hi> hath alotted us. And our life here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) Militant, under our Great Captain and <hi>General God Almighty,</hi> our part is not to diſpute or offer Councel; but to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35552:38"/>his orders, whether it be to dig in the Trenches, or ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Watch, or Fight. Finally, it doth not belong to us to chooſe our parts, but to act them. And <hi>God</hi> appointing us time, and place, and the Part we are to act upon the Theater of the World, we ought to apply our ſelves to the fitteſt means of repreſenting that part alotted to us, not to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us to murmur and repine at it, eſpecially, conſidering that it is his pleaſure we ſhould do ſo, to whom we owe our ſelves, and whoſe <hi>Will</hi> we dayly pray may <hi>be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We ought to be Content in, and chearfully ſubmit to, the will and pleaſure of <hi>God,</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as an <hi>Allwiſe Being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>God Almighty</hi> is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Sovereign Lord
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35552:39"/>of Heaven and Earth,, the great diſpencer and Ruler of all events, in the world; ſo likewiſe is he a moſt Juſt and <hi>Allwiſe Being;</hi> And therefore we ought not only to ſubmit to his Will, as 'tis an act of neceſſity, which we cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, or as an act of obedience to our Sovereign; but as an act of choice and of prudence, becauſe our Maker is infinitely wiſer than our ſelves, and perfectly to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fowed, and obey'd. For what is choſen be the Wiſdom of <hi>God</hi> muſt be infinitely better then what we chuſe; 'tis certainly much more prudently done to commit our ſelves to God for Councel, Guidance, and Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than to be left to the headi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and blindneſs of our own councels, and to eat the bitter fruit of our own raſhneſs and folly.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:35552:39"/>
            <p>For we may (eſpecially in ſome late horrid Inſtances) eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, what ſmall occurrencies quite ſhatter and diſorder and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn the moſt Politick, Subtile, Secret, and Well-laid deſigns in the world. And notwithſtanding the long deliberation, &amp; forecaſt, the huge proſpect and foreſight of difficulties, the great reſerves and preparations againſt all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obſtacles; in a word, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the advantages of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, Secrecy, Combination of Parties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> one poor unthought of Accident, craks in ſunder, and disjoynts, the whole Elaborate project, Deſtroyes and Ruines the Great Deſign. <hi>God Almighty</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by telling us, that the Actions of men, and their ſucceſſes are in the power of the Divine Will, and teaching us not to truſt to our own wiſdom, in contriving and cutting
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35552:40"/>out our own Fortunes, but to caſt our care opon him, who knows better then we what is fitteſt for us. Now unleſs we could imagine our ſelves wiſer then God, it will alwaies be our Duty to reſolve our poor, narrow, improvident wills, into the will of the Moſt Wiſe <hi>God;</hi> who will not ſuffer any hurt or evil, to befall us, unleſs it be for ſome greater good upon another account. For tho ſome particular diſpenſations of Providence may ſeem unto us to be difficult and obſcure, <hi>His Judgments being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable, and his waies paſt finding out;</hi> yet we may be moſt ſure, there is an Excellent Contrivance in all of them; and there are Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Reaſons and Ends, whereby the Wiſdom of ſuch Diſpenſations may be Juſtified. As, to quicken our Relliſh of, and our Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for, thoſe mercies we enjoy;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35552:40"/>to Teach us reſignation to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will; to Enlarge our Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; to prevent the ſurfeits of Proſperity, and awaken as it were with Thunder, our Drowzy Souls, that have long ſlept too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely in Sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, we may conſider Afflictions, as oft times the occaſions of great temporal advantages. And we muſt not look upon them, as they ſit heavy upon us, but as they ſerve ſome of <hi>Gods</hi> ends, and the Purpoſes of Univerſal Providence. Thus once a noble Heathen, after he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced the great Advantage his Baniſhment gave him, as to his Temporal preferment, cryed out, <hi>Periiſſem, ni periiſſem.</hi> Thus if a man could have opened one of the Pages of the Divine Councel, and there read the Event of <hi>Joſephs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſold to the Merchants of <hi>Midi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> he might with great reaſon
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35552:41"/>have dryed up the young-man's tears; And we may from an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of inſtances ſafely conclude that <hi>God</hi> eſteems it one of his peculiar Glories to bring Good out of Evil.</p>
            <p>So that whatever 'tis God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points for us, 'tis not onely fit for us to ſubmit to, but to chooſe, and chearfully, and thankfully, as well as patiently and quietly, to follow and embrace. And however trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, uneaſy and grievous, the Diſpenſations of Providence are to us, we ought patiently to acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce in them, and wait upon <hi>God's</hi> All-ſufficiency and Goodneſs, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to remove them in his good time, or to ſupport us under them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We ought to ſubmit to the will and pleaſure of Almighty <hi>God</hi> in the afflicting us, upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his <hi>Infinite Goodneſs;</hi> and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35552:41"/>this in point of common gratitude. For if Afflictions be certainly ſent as a real favour and kindneſs; If (according to the Royal Prophet) <hi>God</hi> does indeed love thoſe whom he chaſtizes; Then they ought to be received with gratitude and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, not murmuring and repining. For the return of thanks (the leaſt and meaneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital) is indiſpenſibly due to kindneſs received; And you will ſcarce meet with a man ſo much a ſtranger to the common Rules of Civility, as not gratefully to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and acknowledge a favour done him; or ſo void of humanity, as to be angry or vext, with any perſon, for being too much his Friend. Affliction therefore ſent out of <hi>Love,</hi> ought to be received with thankfulneſs. Now 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true, that Affliction cometh from <hi>God</hi>'s Love. For its
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35552:42"/>end is to amend and better the man; and we may undeniably conclude, that God loves him whom he does good to, whom he labours and endeavours to ſave, and make happy with his own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. Afflictions (ſays a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Moraliſt) are like a Friends Reproof, or a Fathers Correction, trouble the man into Amendment, pinch the Soul into greater Purity. They make us more humble, watchful and careful; draw us of from too much reſting on the world; make us bethink us of our Duty, and return to God by Repentance and Obedience. Thus ſo long as God Almighty is pleaſed to afflict us, 'tis plain we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Diſcipline, under his care. No man's Condition is deſperate, ſo long as the Phyſitian continues his Adminiſtration, nor is any man wholly forſaken of <hi>God</hi> nor
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35552:42"/>paſt his care, ſo long as he is under Affliction, for this is a Medicine, that without our own default will certainly recover, or better us.</p>
            <p>If a Good man be not bleſt with Succeſs and Proſperity, yet even his Croſſes and Diſappointments are turn'd into Bleſſings; as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him more humble, and leſs eſteeming, this preſent world. An Eminent Example of this we have in the perſon of our late Martyr'd Sovereign. His Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment was the happieſt time of his life to him. There it was that inſtead of a Priſon, he begun to find a paſſage into Liberty and true Freedome, and thoſe better thoughts which the croud of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Intanglements of Intereſt had barr'd from his mind; His meeting now with no ſuch reſiſtance, but being quickned from his preſent misfortune,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35552:43"/>wrought Reſolutions in him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a Chriſtian, and a Martyr. There did the Vanity of the world, the Folly of humane great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with all that is ſplendid on this ſide Immortality, diſcover it ſelf free from that falſe Varniſh, that had formerly wrought too much upon humane Infirmity. This raiſed in him a juſt undervaluing and loathing of the bewitching, but deceiving Charms of this world; And this made him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>Gods</hi> great Goodneſs to him in that reſtraint. Thus 'tis an Everlaſting truth, that—<hi>All things work together for the beſt to them that love, and fear God:</hi> Thus Afflictions you ſee come for the good and amendment even of good men, are always ſent for our inſtruction or prevention of Sin, and 'tis our fault and weakneſs, if they have not the bleſſed effect.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35552:43"/>Now ſince there are few or no perſons, who have been obſervant of <hi>Gods</hi> dealing towards them, but are able to ſay from their own Experience, —'<hi>Tis good for them, that they have been afflicted;</hi> We have reaſon to be thankful for them, at leaſt to receive them with Submiſſion, Patience and Content. Eſpecially conſidering that <hi>God</hi> owes us nothing, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no obligation, no law of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring benefits upon us, but all that we have, we have of free gift and bounty: And Morality tells us, that if we receive an <hi>Alms</hi> from another, it is very reaſonable that we ſhould be content, with what the other pleaſes to give, without preſcribing to his Liberality.</p>
            <p>The beſt of men are Sinners, and therefore deſerve far worſe at the hands of <hi>God,</hi> than the worſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, that do or can befall any
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35552:44"/>man in this life. If we therefore be not ſo happy, as we deſire, it is well we are not ſo miſerable as we deſerve; if things go not ſo well, as we could wiſh they had done, its well they are not ſo ill as they might juſtly have been. And the worſt we here ſuffer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſs then we deſerve, and the leaſt we enjoy more than we can in Juſtice expect; We ought in reaſon to be content and thankful for the leaſt Mercy; And to be patient and humble under the greateſt Evil.</p>
            <p>There have been Examples of great Afflictions, that have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen better men then we are And when our Condition is at the worſt, 'tis much better than we deſerve, or what many others, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then we, enjoy. The Evils then we ſuffer, being much ſhort of our Demerit, the Good we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35552:44"/>much beyond what we Deſerve, what abſolute and indiſpenſible Neceſſity, lies upon us to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with our Condition, though Afflicted or Poor! For though we want ſomething that others have, yet we have ſomewhat (by the Bounty of God) that many as good, if not better, want. We ſhould learn Contentment by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering others wants, and our own Enjoyments; And not learn diſcontent from others Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and our own Wants.</p>
            <p>Men would queſtionleſs be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient under Sufferings of any kind, if they carried with them, a due ſenſe of their unworthineſs; and upon a judicious account look'd upon their meaneſt, loweſt, worſt Condition, as better than they deſerv'd at the hands of <hi>God.</hi> The beſt of Mankind may eaſily find, that all that which was truly Good
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35552:45"/>thro the whole Courſe of his life, is a pitiful, ſlender Scant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and would be infinitely out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh'd by his Sins, Omiſſions and Defects. And the due Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon and Proſpect of this, would quickly give him a ſeaſonable lecture, of humility and patience. And there's no man but upon a ſtrict and impartial ſearch of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, may find enough to deſerve Affliction, ſomewhat amiſs that requires amendment, ſome Evils growing into Exorbitancy; in a word, Corruptions enouth to grow into greater Enormities; which the All-ſeeing God knows, and in mercy, and goodneſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents by the <hi>Corroſives</hi> and <hi>Cathar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> of Affliction. So great and conſtant is his love to us, even in his puniſhing us! How many dayly Sins and Offences do we continually ſtand guilty of? How
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35552:45"/>many contempts and abuſes of Spiritual and Temporal Bleſſings, have we to anſwer for? And yet <hi>God</hi> does not puniſh theſe with an utter deprivation of them. Nay, Corruption and Vice is con-genial with our very <hi>Being.</hi> In every year you will find the Iniquity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to that Age, And as we improve in Stature, Age, and Knowledge, our Sins are rather varied, and chang'd, then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken. And yet God does not (as moſt juſtly he might) cut us off in the midſt of our Iniquities, but ſpares, and gives us time and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for Repentance. Now if he be thus patient towards us in our ſinning againſt him, when we oppoſe and provoke him, 'tis but reaſon that we ſhould be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, in our ſufferings from him, when he endeavours to heal and reclaim us.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:35552:46"/>
            <p>To Conclude: Gods Love and Goodneſs ſtill continues even in Affliction; for he hath ordain'd, after a few years or days thus ſpent, after a few Afflictions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone, with Chriſtian Courage and Fortitude, An Eternal State of unchangeable and perfect hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. And Death the worſt of temporal Evils will cure all theſe maladies, and deliver up the ſoul into a ſtate of endleſs comfort and felicity.</p>
            <p>I Promis'd, <hi>Sir,</hi> in this ſhort Diſcourſe to confine my ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Rules of mere Morality, and I think I have been juſt to my Reſolution. As to the Firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, about <hi>Regulation of Paſſions,</hi> it is acknowledged to be a <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> Theme, and that nothing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt can be writ upon that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which will nor fall within
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35552:46"/>the proper and peculiar Province of a Moraliſt. As to the Second Propoſition, Touching Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>God,</hi> and Acquieſcence in his pleaſure, at all times, and in all things; I will (upon your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire) give you the Names of thoſe Heathen Moraliſts, whoſe write<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings do Authorize moſt of what I have here ſet down. And how far bare Morality has gone in this point, I ſhall in Concluſion of all repreſent to you in the words of a Heathen Poet.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Juvenal. Satyr <hi>10.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>Permittes ipſis expendere numinibus, quid</l>
               <l>Conveniat nobis, rebuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſit utile noſtris-</l>
               <l>Nam pro Jucundis aptiſſima, &amp;c.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:35552:47"/>
               <head>Boyle's Seraphick Love, <hi>pag. 31.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>Unto the Wiſer God's the Care permit,</l>
               <l>Of what's for us and our affairs moſt ſit.</l>
               <l>They will for Pleaſant things the Beſt confer,</l>
               <l>To whom man is, than to himſelf, more dear;</l>
               <l>We by our blinder Paſſions led aſtray</l>
               <l>Do for a <hi>Wife,</hi> perhaps, or <hi>Children</hi> pray.</l>
               <l>Which they may chance refuſe us our of love,</l>
               <l>Knowing what both the <hi>Wife</hi> and <hi>Boyes</hi> would prove.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:35552:47"/>
            <p>I pray God Grant that theſe, and the like Conſiderations (which I hope will work the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe they come from your Son) may be effectual to create holy reſolutions in you, Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly to bear what ever <hi>God</hi> pleaſes to lay on you. And may Heaven beſtow on you ſuch an Entire and Perfect Reſignation of your ſelf to Providence, ſuch a chearful acquieſcence in that ſtate and condition of life, <hi>God</hi> hath placed you in; ſuch truely Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Patience under Afflictions, that being in a Conſtant Ready<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with ſatisfaction and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to receive whatever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from his Will, and alwaies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his Wiſdom, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Juſtice in all his deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings towards you, your life may be as comfortable and happy, as tis
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35552:48"/>capable of being in this world; and moſt excellently diſpoſed for a better in Glory. I am, with all imaginable Duty, and Obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt entirely Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Son &amp; Servant, <hi>R. S.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Qu. <hi>Coll.</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. <date>
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 20. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:35552:48"/>
            <head>A Prayer for Submiſſion to the Divine Will.</head>
            <p>BLeſſed Lord, who knoweſt what is fit for us better then our ſelves, and loveſt us more truly then we do our ſelves; into thy hands I reſign my Soul and Body, Will and Affections, all I am and have in the World. Deal with me and mine, as ſhall ſeem expedient to thy godly Wiſdom. Leave me not in the hands of my own counſel, my own hurtful devices and fancies, as a ſore puniſhment for my Sin: but take me wholly to thy ſelf; diſpoſe and order me after thy own good pleaſure. And make me not only ſenſible of thy love in all thy dealings with me, but alſo thankful to Thee for the ſame, through Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer for Contentment.</head>
            <p>ALmighty God, who art kind even to the unthankful and to the evil, I humble my ſelf in the duſt before thee;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35552:49"/>bewailing earneſtly the ſecret riſings of my heart againſt Thee, my vile miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and hard thoughts of thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. Thou knoweſt the anguiſh of my Soul; O Lord pardon, O Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give. Suffer me not, O my God, to be loſt in my own wild murmurings and repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; but draw me graciouſly to thy ſelf. Open mine Eyes, that in all theſe Croſſes of mine I may diſcern thy Love; and enable me by thy grace to welcom them, as ſo many ſpecial marks and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of thy favour. 'Tis of very faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs Thou haſt cauſed me to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; O make me ſenſible of thy mercy. Send out thy light and thy truth, that I may ſee the wonderful bleſſings I enjoy, and continually praiſe Thee for them. Reconcile me daily more and more to my preſent Condition. 'Tis the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thou haſt plac'd me in: tis fit and proper for me, thou who art infinitely wiſe haſt alotted it: and thou art ever gracious in thy alotments, 'tis the very beſt Condition I am capable of: Lord make me thankful. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35552:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
